hey what's up guys my name is Jonah and
welcome back to my safe loss loss series
so today we're going to be talking all
about templates and I know that you guys
have been requesting this for a while
but it is kind of an advanced topic so I
didn't want to jump into it too quickly
but today we're finally going to start
off with a fairly gentle introduction to
templates in C++ so first of all what is
a template well those of you familiar
with other languages might see this as
kind of generics Riesling Java or C
sharp they're kind of called generic
templates are completely different well
they're not completely different but
they are like infinitely more powerful
than generics in those managed languages
right templates are almost like a bit of
a macro they let you do pretty much
anything whereas generics is very
heavily limited by the type system and
by a lot of other factors templates
specifically are much more powerful and
we're gonna see this as we go along
don't worry I'm gonna probably end up
having like dozens of videos on
templates or something like that so by
no means is this gonna be the only video
I make on templates templates are such a
huge and complex topic and can be
incredibly crazy so we're gonna be
exploring all of that as a serious goes
on so first of all well what is a
template a template basically allows you
to define a template that will be
compiled but like by your usage if that
makes sense you can get the compiler to
write code for you based on a set of
rules that's really what a template is
just the compiler writing code for you
based on the rules that you've given it
when I write a function for example and
I use a template in that function what
I'm actually doing is creating almost
like a blueprint so that what I decide
to call that function I can specify
certain parameters which determine what
code actually gets put into the template
and that is all kind of determined by
the way that I actually use that
function again it's a little bit
difficult to explain and in fact I could
just give you the definition that's on
like say BP reference or on Wikipedia
I'm trying not to do that obviously I
think the best way is just gonna be to
show you what it actually looks like in
the code so a good example of why I
might want to use a template is if I
want to create a function that is
largely going to be the same but may
take in different types maybe I have a
print
that I want to use to print integers so
I might do something like print in value
and all this is gonna do is see out my
value and if I go back down to main I
can call print with a value such as five
and everything will be fine now what if
I want to actually use a string there
instead like Hello so suddenly I need to
actually define another overload for
this function which actually takes in a
string so just like this note that I'm
actually passing this string by value
here because I want to kind of have it
be the same as my print function here
which also takes in the integer by value
then I'm going to basically end up
copying and pasting this code this works
fine in order for this to actually
compile though we do need to include
string now what if I want to print a
float well you kind of are seeing the
picture here I hope if I want to print a
float like five point five then I also
need to basically copy and paste this
function again so now I have three
different functions here which basically
the only thing that changes here is the
actual type of data I'm passing in
because C out can of course accept any
kind of primitive or or built-in C++
type that we're actually using here so
what we've ended up with is manually
defining three different overloads for a
print function that's okay some people
actually prefer to do it this way but
what if we could just define that
function once a good goal for software
engineering in general really is to kind
of avoid code duplication right because
if we decide to actually change one of
these print functions to do something
extraordinary we decide to go from using
C out to print air for one of our own
custom logging functions we have to
change it in all of the places that
we've actually defined that right so in
this case in all three print functions
we have to actually just occurred what
if we could just write that code once
and then somehow be able to fill in the
blank for the type that's where we can
use a template so instead of writing
this code this many times what I'm
actually going to do is just convert
this into being a template the way that
we do this in tactically is before the
return type we write template then open
an angular bracket type name and then
give it a name
typically T is used and then finally we
can use T instead of our actual type
over here so this becomes void print T
value
suddenly if I actually compile this code
by hitting ctrl f7 you can see it
compiles just fine and if in fact if I
run my try by hitting f5 look at that
all three all three functions actually
work even though we've just written one
function so how on earth does this work
and what's actually happening here well
the first thing that gives away that
this is an actual template is well the
word template right this means that this
is a template that will be evaluated at
compile time so basically this is an
actual code this isn't actually a real
function this only gets created when we
actually call it and when we call it
based on how we call it with what types
does this actually get created and
compiled as source code now this next
part is something called a template
parameter in this case we've chosen to
use type name as the type of template
parameter and then T is just a name so
this could be anything we could call
this type with the call this churn over
the course anything we really wanted to
and so what happens is this specific
variable name this template kind of
argument name we can use that throughout
our actual template code to substitute
whatever type in this case gets used so
what we've done is instead of just
writing int value like that where we've
written T value which means that when we
actually call this code whatever type we
specify here is the type that actually
goes into this argument now this is a
little bit harder to read in this case
because when I actually specifying the
type explicitly it's just kind of
getting it implicitly from the actual
parameters here in this case but what we
can do is when we call print we can
actually specify using angular brackets
here the type that we want so for
example print int if I let's just get
rid of these and keep it real simple for
now so what we've done here is we've
pulled the print function with the type
int this this template argument here
accepts a type name now you can also
write this as class by the way it is
exactly the same synonymous right class
class type name I tend to use type name
because class by just reading the code
class kind of implies that it has to be
a class type that's not true as you can
see this coastal compiles even though
I'm using int so because of that I tend
to just use type name because it just
makes more
so we write type name T which means that
the first half of that argument that we
have here is an actual type so we can
write end here we can write STD string
we can write whatever we want obviously
if we write STD string then what
actually happens as T gets replaced with
the type that we've specified STD string
which means that we are obviously are
taking in a string value hence why this
code is not compiling so we actually
have to write something here like China
or something now if we go back to our
five example we can specify int here but
we don't have to if it's possible for
the type to actually be worked out by
the argument that we use here either by
the return value which which we can talk
about later or by the actual parameter
here so in other words a plus boss knows
that five is an integer it can
automatically deduce what type T should
be which is why we don't actually have
to specify it using those angular
brackets which makes our job a bit even
easier now that being said let me show
you explicitly what actually happens if
you do not write anything so I'm not
using this print function at all this
print function does not really exist
this print function is just a template
which actually gets created when we call
the print function with the given
template argument and I can even prove
this by making a syntax error here so
let's just say instead of value I forget
not a know the e or something so I'm
just printing value now clearly this is
an error because there is no variable
called value so if I hit control f7 to
compile my code look at that it compiles
just fine and that's because the
template doesn't really exist until we
call it if I go back to my code and I
actually try and call print with like
the value 5 or something and hit control
f7
at that point you can see I actually do
get an error here telling me the value
is an undeclared identifier and again
that's because the template only gets
created when we actually call it because
it's just a template it's not actual
card it gets materialized I guess into
real code that gets sent to the compiler
and compiled based on the usage of the
template now MSV c won't tell you about
errors in templates that you're not
actually using some compilers like clang
actually will so it is kind of compiled
dependent but in this case you can see
we don't actually get any errors we've
written code that's not really correct
but until we call the template it
doesn't exist so we don't get any
compiler errors so what actually happens
when we compile this template is it
knows in this case that we have used
five here right which means that the
type name is actually an integer so what
happens is it basically fills in the
blanks here so it would be equivalent as
to if we just copied and pasted this
method and then replace T with an actual
int because that's what we're calling
here and now this is a real function
that has to get linked and everything
when we actually compile and Link this
code so let's just fix that syntax error
we had there and that is actually what
happens in this case now when we call
print with a different argument like a
flirt for example another version of
this template actually gets created so
this gets copied and pasted and then
instead of T this time we're using a
flirt so you kind of get the picture
really all this is is a template
specifying how to create methods and
these methods all these functions can be
created or automatically by the compiler
based on your usage of them which is
pretty cool now templates are by no
means just limited to types or anything
like that and they're not limited to
functions either you can actually create
entire classes based on templates and in
fact that's a lot of what the standard
template library actually is in C++ it's
just completely using templates let's
take a look at an example where we're
not actually using a type as a template
argument and let's do it for a class
instead of for a function let's just get
rid of this print function that we've
created over here and let's create a
class suppose that I wanted to create an
array but I wanted this array class to
actually be created on the stack so what
I basically mean is let's just create a
class called array and then over here
maybe it's an integer array in this case
I actually want to have an array that
has some kind of size that is determined
at compile time now I can't just kind of
put in a variable size or anything like
that because since this is a stack
allocated array it actually has to be
known at compile time now obviously we
could use alakay or something like that
to grow the stack dynamically we're not
going to use any of that in this example
we just want to basically create a
normal
kind of see style array on the stack so
this size value does in fact have to be
known at compile time now templates are
evaluated at compile time so this is
perfect what I can do is convert this
class into being a template but instead
of using type name as it as my template
argument I can actually use just an
integer right I'll call this n which is
basically just as for number and then
instead of size over here I'm going to
write n and then finally I'll just add
one public function to this array which
is just going to return the size of the
array so I'll write int get size and
then I'll just return and okay so what's
going to happen here is exactly the same
thing that actually happened with our
function when we call this array and we
specify a size like five and I'll just
call this array what happens is if this
card gets compiled based on its usage so
in this case five is the template
argument which means that a version of
this class gets created which replaces n
with five like that and like that so
this is actually what we end up with
this is the code that we end up with and
then of course if I call a raid or get
size here and print that to the console
or get rid of this extra copy I've
created here that's my card let's hit f5
you can see that I get five printing so
that's how it works so you can see that
we don't just have to use types we can
even use integers or other data types to
basically specify how we want to
generate a class an entire class in this
case let's go one step further suppose
it is said of this being an INT
explicitly oh I also wanted to make the
type actually variable so I wanted to be
able to specify what type this array
actually contains at compile time well I
can add another template arguments let's
add this one before the number so I'll
just write type name T and then int n
right so now I'm going to replace this
int with T and suddenly what I've got is
an array of type T which is specified at
compile time by the template that is of
size n which is also specified by
compile times so now over here what I
actually call this array I have to
specify int as an example and five for
my size and I can obviously change this
to be anything I want like SAEs string
and 50 or whatever and you can see that
what I've created is kind of a class
that gets automatically created every
time I actually use this array so that's
pretty cool and what we've actually
created
is very similar to how the standard
array class actually works in the
standard template library that say the
say plus plus right it just has two
template arguments type and size and it
creates an array very similar to the way
that we've actually done it here now
this is a sort of matter programming in
C++ because you can see instead of
actually programming what our code does
at runtime were kind of programming what
the compiler will actually do during
compile time and this is extremely
powerful now what we're doing here I
think this is a pretty good kind of
gentle introduction we've even kind of
gone as far as to create multiple
template arguments and use integers
instead of just kind of type names but
this is just scratching the surface I
mean this can get really crazy really
quickly and because of that I kind of
want to talk about where you might want
to use templates and where you might not
want to use templates so this part is
kind of entirely subjective it's
opinionated but in my experience this is
this is how it works right
so first of all a whole bunch of game
studios out there or software companies
whatever actually just outright down
templates they say never use templates
ever now I think that's a little bit
kind of overreacting to the situation
because I think the templates can be
extremely useful for situations where
like I don't know like a logging system
or something like that you have every
possible type that you want to log do
you really have to like specify an
overload for every single function well
you can automate that with templates
right you can get the compiler to write
code for you based on a set of rules
that's really what a template is just
the compiler writing code for you based
on the rules that you've given it and
based on the usage of that function or
class or anything like that right that
being said if you start using templates
if you start getting really really
complex with your templates and you
start just having it generate an entire
like meta language for you and I've seen
code that would probably give you
nightmares like seriously you can go
really far with templates that might be
pushing it right that might be going a
little bit too far because there's a
point where the templates become so
complex that if there's an issue with it
no one can understand what's going
and you'll literally have to just get
like a notebook get a piece of paper and
start filling in all these types
manually of course you can get the
compiler to actually tell you what code
is generating and all of that but even
so like at work we've had cases where
we've just had to sit down and spend
three hours figuring out what code has
actually been compiled and what's going
on with our templates and why they're
not working when that happens I think
you've gone too far
and I don't think that you should get
too crazy with templates even though you
can there is a point where doing things
manually and writing out code yourself
is actually going to benefit you and
your team a lot more than trying to
create this massive template magic that
just does everything for you but is kind
of fragile and very difficult to
understand so I don't think the template
should be completely banned but I also
don't think that you should go crazy
templates and abuse them a lot anyway
we're gonna have a lot more videos about
templates because there's a lot more
than I want to talk about is just
scratching the surface once we actually
get into kind of the game engine series
as well will people start to see real
examples of where we might want to use
templates off the top of my head I think
two kind of really important places
where I would definitely use templates
are things like logging systems and also
even like a material system like for
rendering graphics right when you have a
uniform buffer that can contain various
different types templating that to an
extent can be extremely useful anyway I
hope you guys enjoy this video if you
did you can hit that like button you can
also you can you can help support this
series in all the series that I make
here on my channel by going to pay for a
Mac on 4/2 Cherno massive shout out as
always to all the wonderful supporters
that helped make this possible there are
some pretty cool rewards that you can
get such as access to all the source
code from my OpenGL series as well as
the soon to come game engine series by
supporting then you also get like for
the top tier supporters we do this thing
while we basically hang out for an hour
once a month and we just talk about
whatever the next one is actually coming
up in like a week so definitely sign up
for that if you're interested and then
also you'll get videos early and a whole
bunch of other rewards but most of all
you're helping to support this series
which is awesome because I can basically
just lets me make more videos you can
also join discord I have just called
server over
- sherrilyn home slash discord that's
basically just a community of people
where you can talk about whatever you
want including this programming stuff
and just discuss it with other people
ask for help with your kirtan all that
definitely encourage you guys to join
that and as always I will see you in the
next video goodbye
[Music]